.
>> good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to the APRIL 8th 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Yes.
Supervisor chan chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor and engardio
engardio present supervisor
fielder field are present
supervisor mahmood mahmood
present supervisor mendelson
present mendelson present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sardar
sardar not present supervisor
cheryl cheryl present
supervisor walton walton
present MR. PRESIDENT you have
a quorum.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> supervisor so
der is
attending to his newborn.
>> can we have a motion to
excused supervisor sader from
today's meeting moved by chen
seconded by melgar and I think
without objection we can
approve that motion.
>> the san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the two colony who
are the original inhabitants of
the san francisco peninsula as
the indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the
ramakrishna loney have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsibility as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homelands.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
romita saloni community and by
affirming their sovereign
rights as first peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in saying the pledge of america
in general is just an
expression of the physical and.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at us S.F. Gov tv
and especially today kaleena
mendoza who record each of our
meetings and make the
transcripts available to the
public online.
>> and I believe our next item
is approval of minutes.
Yes.
Today we are told the board
will be considering the
FEBRUARY 25th 2025 and MARCH
4th, 2025 board meeting minutes
rates.
Colleagues, do we have any
changes to the minutes?
I don't see any one seeing
none.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented moved
by cheryl is there a second
seconded by chan?
And MADAM Clerk will you please
call the roll on the minutes
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio
and engardio I supervisor
filter filter I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin high mandolin I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor cheryl cheryl either
nice then without a without
objection the minutes will be
approved after public comment
as presented and MADAM Clerk I
skipped over communications do
we have any communications?
>> yes, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance at this meeting
in the board's legislative
chamber room two 52nd floor
and city hall.
You MAY also watch the
proceedings on S.F. Gov tv's
channel 26 or view the
livestream at w w w dot S.F.
Gov tv borg to submit your
public comments send an email
to p o s at S.F. Gop borg or
via U.S. Postal service to the
san francisco board of
supervisors number one DR.
Carlton b good place city hall
room 244 san francisco,
california 94102 to make a
reasonable accommodation
request under the americans
with disabilities act order
request language assistant
please call the clerk's office
at least two business days
in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
And finally, MR. PRESIDENT, our
office is in receipt of an ada
accommodation requests to
provide their comments as a
first speaker during general
public comment when general
public comment is called we
will pull that request your
first.
>> that concludes my
communication.
Thank you MADAM Clerk let's go
to our consent agenda items one
through nine items one through
nine comply comprise the
consent agenda.
>> colleagues does anyone want
to sever any items from the
consent agenda?
I don't see anyone on the
roster.
MADAM Clerk can you please call
the roll on items one through
nine supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio engardio I
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor mandarin hai menzel
I supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor cheryl cheryl either
tonight without objection these
ordinances are passed on first
reading and the resolutions are
adopted MADAME Clerk let's go
to our regular agenda new
business item ten.
>> item number ten is a
resolution approving the police
commission statement of purpose
pursuant to charter section 4.1
or 2 to all right colleagues, I
think we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> and MADAM Clerk, will you
please call item 11?
Item number 11 is a resolution
approving the port commission
lease l 17 180 with everett
jones barbecue S.F.
International for a two storey
restaurant space located at 300
jefferson street for a term of
ten years at the rental rate of
5% of gross revenues for the
first year and no less than
10,000 per month with
incremental increases
thereafter.
>> and let's take this item
same house, same call without
objection, this resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 12?
>> item number 12 is the
resolution authorizing the
execution and delivery of
multifamily housing revenue
notes in an aggregate principal
amount not to exceed 64 million
for the construction of a 92
unit multifamily rental housing
project known as 850 turk.
Approving a funding loan
agreement a borrower loan
agreement and a regulatory
agreement and decorative of
restrictive covenants of the
project.
>> okay let's take this item
same house, same call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> and MADAM Clerk, please call
item number 13 item number 13
is a resolution approving
and authorizing the director of
the mayor's office of housing
and community development with
hazel eddie woolsey to execute
documents relating to a loan
in an aggregate total amount
not to exceed approximately
11.6 million to finance three
existing affordable multifamily
rental housing projects for low
income households known as a
burnell bundle located at 1652
to 1654 eddy street 30 3554
17th street and 195 woolsey
street and making appropriate
findings.
Let's take this item same
house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted MADAM Clerk please call
item 14.
>> item number 14 is a
resolution authorizing the
department of technology chief
information officer to enter a
no cost a memorandum of
understanding under which the
city will provide feedback to
innovate U.S. And which will
grant innovate U.S. A right to
use the city's feedback for any
purpose for a two year term.
>> and we'll take this item
same house, same call.
Without objection, this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 15?
>> item number 15 is a
resolution to authorize the
mayor.
The mayor's chief of staff.
Chief of infrastructure.
Assistant chief of
infrastructure.
Chief of housing and economic
development.
Director of public affairs
and policy advisor and the
general manager of the director
and staff of our pd's
partnership division our
director of capital
and planning our beatty's india
basin project manager and R.P.
Dees india basin equitable
development plan manager to
solicit donations for the india
basin waterfront park
initiative from nonprofits,
private organizations as grant
makers and foundations for six
months notwithstanding the
behest id payment ordinance
and we will take this item.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 16?
>> item number 16 is an
ordinance amending the
administrative code to create
the castro upper market
entertainment zone.
And clarify the boundaries of
vegas's existing arena
entertainment zone and making
appropriate findings.
>> we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection, this ordinance is
passed on first reading.
MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 17?
>> item number 17 is a motion
appointing america nichelle
sanchez term ending APRIL 27th
2026 to the sunshine ordinance
task force.
We'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection this motion is
approved.
>> MADAME Clerk, can you please
call item 18?
>> item number 18 is a motion
approving the treasurer's
nomination of megan wallace to
the treasury oversight
committee term ending JUNE
17th, 2026.
>> and we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection this motion is also
approved.
>> and MADAM Clerk, let's go to
our committee reports.
>> item 23 was considered by
the land use and transportation
committee at a regular meeting
on monday, APRIL 7th, 2025
and was recommended to the full
board.
Item 23 is an ordinance
amending the planning code
and zoning map to establish the
600 townsend street west
special use district to allow
the legalization of the
longstanding office uses at the
site and making appropriate
findings.
>> we'll take this item same
house, same call.
Without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading.
>> and MADAM Clerk, let's go to
roll call.
>> I think first up on roll
call for introductions is
supervisor walton submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton supervisor
chan.
Thank you.
Supervisor chan.
Supervisor chen.
>> hi colleagues.
Today I am introducing a
resolution affirming that the
support of board of supervisors
for an affordable housing site
is strategy that ensures that
we make proactive
and meaningful progress towards
our affordable housing goals.
>> as our city engages in the
conversation around rezoning
the housing opportunity area
and priority equity geographies
and affordable housing side
strategy, it is critical to
create housing at all income
levels including hundred
percent affordable
and preservation projects
throughout our neighborhood
commercial sales and transit
corridors.
There are many untapped it
opportunities sites for 100%
affordable housing and housing
preservation projects many of
which struggle to complete
against for profit developers
and investors to acquire sites
as an affordable housing site
strategy is something that we
signed up for in our housing
elements in policy actions.
>> 1.2.2-1.2.6 and it's
critical to achieving our
affirmatively furthering fair
housing goals.
It will recommend strategies
for identifying acquiring
and maintaining such suitable
locations for affordable
housing citywide informed by
community needs financial
feasibility and programmatic
realities.
>> it will provide an
opportunity to incentivize
strategy for developing
specific type of sites such as
public lands and property owned
by religious and nonprofit
organizations as well as best
practices for site acquisition,
rezoning, public land use
and public and private
partnership throughout san
francisco, the planning
department and the mayor's
office of housing and community
development have begun to
develop a site strategy
and this resolution urge this
department to bring this effort
to fruition and also to present
the strategy to the board of
supervisors.
And I'm looking forward to
support for this resolution
from my colleagues and want to
thank supervisor fielder
and supervisor connie chen for
their early co-sponsorship.
The rest I submit thank you.
>> thank you supervisor chen
supervisor dorsey submit thank
you supervisor and engardio.
Thank you supervisor fielder.
Thank you supervisor mahmood
colleagues I have a very
special resolution to introduce
today that is deeply personal
to me.
I'd like to introduce a
resolution declaring APRIL
autism awareness month.
>> last month I toured the ark
san francisco and supervisor
dorsey's district which is a
leader in advocating for
residents with learning
and developmental disabilities
including autism and was
reminded of the incredible
outcomes we have when people
are met where they're at
and provided specialized
support to help them thrive.
>> they have a youth achieve
program which partners with us
a few esty and focuses on the
transition from high school to
employment ensuring that
individuals of autism gain the
skills and support they need to
thrive in higher education,
jobs and careers a program with
incredible benefits to our city
program such as these show that
we've come a long way and not
only awareness but an
acceptance and stigmatization
of neurodiversity over the past
few years the internet
and social media have played a
role in connecting people on
this and providing the space
for individuals to openly talk
about their experience.
>> but it wasn't always like
this.
I remember growing up the
science around autism was very
one sided in school at stanford
even we were taught the
diagnosis was only found
in white male youth but how it
expresses itself in different
populations wasn't even
considered.
>> we know now that autism is a
spectrum and can express itself
differently by gender, by race
,by culture and with diagnosis
often going undetected
in people of color and women
especially.
>> and my personal experience
for a long time I felt
different from others but
didn't fully understand why
receiving an autism diagnosis
later in life as many are
coming to these these last
couple of years has helped me
understand my differences
and embrace some of them as
strengths from experiencing
them on a tropism to sensory
sensitivities to being
extremely rigid in routines.
I'm choosing to share this part
of myself in the hopes of
de-stigmatizing autism
and showing others especially
our youth that they are not
alone.
Autism spectrum disorder is a
complex developmental condition
that can affect communication
behavior and social interaction
and it affects an estimated 1
in 36 children nationally
and has increased by over 30%
in the past decade in san
francisco alone, according to
the data from the department of
public health and sfi usd.
>> now at a time where we are
in a budget deficit I believe
it is time to double down on
investing in the services that
are necessary for our most
vulnerable communities.
Our neurodivergent and autistic
communities rely on muni as a 4
usd dcf as a lifeline to move
to learn and to work.
When I was at the arc center
the number one question that
everyone brought up to me was
what are you doing to bring
back the 49?
What are you doing to preserve
our service cuts?
And I think what's lost on on
this fast fact facet is that
people who have autism or
in your division are often very
rigid in their routines and a
single disruption of a muni
line taking away a bus stop,
stopping the service at market
street that single change can
be a life altering outcome for
people who are neurodivergent
or autistic.
>> so when we think about the
budget discussions that we have
and whether to preserve muni or
not, think about that these
aren't just line items on a
budget but these are people's
lives being impacted every day.
>> and so today I'm proud to
stand not only as a policymaker
but as someone who lives with
this reality.
The families and the children
in the neurodivergent community
deserve to not only be
recognized but feel supported
by their city so they truly can
succeed and thrive.
>> this resolution combatant
commands local programs
and advocates who work
tirelessly to support
neurodivergent communities by
providing vital services to
families, navigating the
complexities of raising
children with autism, offering
education peer support
and individualized assistance
to ensure that families are
empowered with the resources
that they need.
I'd like to highlight the work
of felton early autism program,
the bay area autism collective
and initiatives such as bridges
from school to work and the arc
san francisco's youths achieve
program.
>> we'd also like to thank the
department and organizations
that have endorsed this
resolution including sheriff
dorsey smith, interim executive
director of S.F. Department of
children, youth and their
families virginia juan guerra
senior director of workforce
inclusion and program optimizer
for the arc san francisco eli
gallatin and his team at the
office of disability
and accessibility and a usd
superintend DR. Maria sue
and her team.
I'd like to thank my colleagues
who co-sponsored supervisor
cheryl dorsey melgar, mandel
min chen chan fielder
and walton.
I'd like to close as well by
thanking those who have reached
out to not only show support
but share your stories this
morning with me.
Experiences around autism neuro
divergence of your families, of
your children and of your loved
ones because that together I
know that we can uplift each
other.
And the response from the
community make me more
confident that we can shift the
narrative and narrative on
autism.
Thank you all for your support
and for advocacy on making
autism awesome.
Thank you.
>> supervisor supervisor
mandarin thank you MADAM Clerk
and thank you for your
introduction.
Supervisor mahmood and it's an
honor to serve with you.
I have a couple of intros.
>> the first is that I'm
introducing a resolution
recognizing APRIL 9th 2025 as
education and sharing day
in san francisco.
Education and sharing day was
first established by the united
states congress in 1978 to
honor the rabbi menachem mendel
schneerson who dedicated his
life to youth education.
The holiday calls for all
americans to reflect on our
commitment to high quality,
accessible education for all.
And I want to thank rabbi
potash at chabad core valley
and district eight for bringing
this day to our attention.
I'm also asking that we adjourn
today's meeting in memory of
david hartzell, an american
quaker peace activist
and district eight resident who
passed away on MARCH 22nd at
the age of 84.
The son of peace movement
activists david dedicated his
life to nonviolent peacemaking
from an early age.
After meeting martin luther
king jr in 1956, he was
inspired to join civil rights
and later anti-vietnam war
movements.
He participated in the 1960s
sit ins and contributed to
peacebuilding efforts in kosovo
.
For nearly two decades he
worked with the american
friends service committee
engaging in nonviolent
peacemaking in the united
states the soviet union, mexico
,the philippines and iran.
>> david later later went on to
lead the peace workers a
network of peace activists
based primarily in san
francisco until his death
in 2002.
He joined peace advocates from
49 countries to officially
establish nonviolent peace
force which deployed its first
civilian protection team to sri
lanka a year later.
In 2014 he founded world beyond
war, an organization that
pursues the abolition of war
through regional organizing
and global campaigns to close
military bases and divest from
corporations that profit from
war rest in peace and power.
David hartzell.
MAY your memory be a blessing.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sartor I'm sorry.
>> supervisor cheryl colleagues
tomorrow marks the 83rd
anniversary of the bataan death
MARCH on APRIL 9th, 19 42
during world war two.
After months of resistance
in the baton peninsula in the
philippines, 75,000 filipino
and american soldiers were
forced to surrender to the
imperial japanese army.
These brave members of the
united states army forces
in the far east endured 99
grueling days of combat only to
be forced upon surrender to
MARCH over 765 miles in brutal
conditions with little food,
medicine or support.
Thousands perished in what is
now remembered as the bataan
death MARCH.
One of the most harrowing
atrocities of world war two.
>> on APRIL 5th my office had
the privilege of attending the
annual bataan remembrance
ceremony remembrance ceremony
at the san francisco national
cemetery in the presidio.
Honoring the courage
and sacrifice of those affected
by the death MARCH as well as
the veterans of world war two
and the korean war.
>> thank you to cecilia galan
galan excuse me and the baton
legacy historical society for
continuing to preserve the
legacy of filipino and american
world war two veterans
and serving as a powerful
reminder of the deep ties
between the filipino
and american peoples.
Both of my grandfathers served
in world war two and their
stories have always reminded me
of the sacrifice and strength
that defined that generation.
But I'm also proud to say that
others on my team have
grandparents who served
in world war two in various
capacities including my aide mc
del rosario, whose grandfather
artemio was a philippine scout
and himself endured the bataan
death MARCH.
Through this resolution the
city and county of san
francisco affirms its
solidarity with the families
veterans and communities that
carry this history forward.
Let us pledge to ensure this
legacy of bravery and sacrifice
never gets forgotten
and endures for generations to
come.
Rest I submit.
Thank you, supervisor.
MR. PRESIDENT, that concludes
roll call for introductions.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
We're running early and so I
guess we will do five minutes
of public comment if anybody
wants to get their public
comment out of the way early.
>> all right.
At this time the board welcomes
general public comment.
Please line up on your right
hand side of the chamber along
the curtains.
You MAY speak to approval of
the minutes as presented.
>> items on the floor adoption
without committee reference
agenda items 26 238 and general
matters that are not on today's
agenda but must be within the
board subject matter
jurisdiction.
>> all other agenda content
will have been reported out to
the board by an appropriate
committee where the public
comment requirement was
satisfied.
As I indicated at the beginning
of the meeting we do have an
accommodation.
>> MR. Kevin lamb could you
please put the caller for
and please confirm you can hear
me and now I will start my
stopwatch which we can hear
you.
>> hello.
This is michael petrelli
calling.
I'd like a moment of silence
please for tony the gay bar
worker who was brutally
attacked on MARCH nine under
the castro theater monkey.
Please.
>> a moment of silence for his
recovery.
>> >> okay.
The moment of silence is over.
Um.
There is a traumatized gay
community in the castro after
this attack on tony and we have
not had cooperation from either
the elected officials in the
district or the police safety
liaison.
Demands have been made for a
town hall where the elected
officials and the police would
listen to our trauma and our
concerns for how to address the
violence that is occurring too
often in the castro, a town
hall would also address the
need to help our homeless
neighbors one of whom died on
the sidewalk earlier this year
.
As we have seen across the
country, fearful republicans do
not hold town hall meetings
because they don't want to face
accountability demands from
their constituents.
Unfortunately this republican
way of not engaged with
constituents is what we see
in the castro and it is harming
the vibrancy and eventual
revival of what we know as the
gay hood.
Yes, the gay hood used to be a
beacon of accountability from
government officials to
worldwide.
Today we need to restore that
vibrancy.
With town hall meetings.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
All right.
>> let's go to their in-person
commenters.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is eric randall, a 25
year resident in district five
,a business owner, gym owner
in district six with an
undergraduate degree
in kinesiology from usf
and also a graduate degree
in kinesiology from S.F. State
.
>> my work has been published
in peer reviewed journals which
includes research on reducing
drug overdose deaths.
I'm here with an urgent plea
for immediate action.
Last FEBRUARY our medical
examiner revealed a devastating
truth.
During black history month,
african-americans less than 5%
of our population accounted for
38% of overdose deaths.
This isn't just a statistic.
It's a crisis demanding a new
approach.
The city of san francisco has
focused on more housing harm
reduction and incarceration for
years.
But in NOVEMBER 2023 something
shifted at you in plaza.
>> we addressed the built
environment.
Drug overdose began to lower
because we offered a healthy
alternative for adults.
I've seen firsthand how
exercise helps individuals cope
and stay sober.
Yet free accessible options are
scarce in other underserved
areas of the city.
We need to replicate the U.N.
Plaza exercise immediately
in the south and market
and lower hill not next spring
but next month.
>> it can be with installing
simple pullup bars on the
sidewalk that take up as much
space as a street sign offering
a no cost immediate way for
residents to manage stress
and build self-efficacy.
>> building potentially before
they see no other option other
than substance use waiving
liability for these health
promoting installations as we
do handing out needles and foil
for harm reduction it's a
crucial step.
Let's invest in proactive
health, not just reactive
crisis response.
Let's build a city that offers
a healthy choice starting now.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
Good afternoon.
I'm anthony garcia.
I'm a new valley resident.
I'm also an army combat
veteran.
I've spent 22 months in iraq.
I was a medical evacuation
officer for eight years while
serving my last tour in iraq.
>> we medevac to approximately
6500 patients in 11 months.
We flew over 4000 combat
missions.
>> it was 90 of us doing this
work.
You could get woken up at three
in the morning or maybe you'd
be fortunate get a mission at
three in the afternoon.
>> we didn't know if people
were alive when we were showing
up half the time, didn't know
what the injuries were, the
wounds.
We were lucky if we had a grid
coordinate callsign.
I'm also a former captain that
led all these professionals.
I got to the army in two
thousand and seven and that's
when I started to let
everything kind of permeate
throughout my my body.
I'm 100% disabled veteran got a
lot of ptsd.
>> the last time that it was a
severe it was when I came out
was in 2020 getting compressed
from the covid outbreak.
i called the va was able to
talk to somebody within 48
hours which I believe prevented
me from killing myself probably
a third time.
>> my fear is that the va will
go away.
There's 26,000 veterans in the
city.
There's 300,000 veterans that
attend the va in san francisco
.
I attended the va in palo alto
prior to moving up here to san
francisco.
The people that work in the va
have a special set of skills
that are designed to help
professionals like myself.
I'm using a lot of very clean
language right now but it
usually doesn't go that way
when you're in the va because a
lot of the military stuff comes
back to you.
>> they know how to handle this
and I'm fearful that my
psychologist that I've had
since 2020 won't be there on
the other end.
I talked to them last thursday.
I thanked them and I expressed
to him that if he was going to
be departing I would like to
know my call to act.
>> my apologies for cutting you
off.
We did the spiritual to make
sure that our intentions are
pretty clear.
>> thank you for your comments
.
You know what he's going to do.
Thank you, sir.
And thank you for your service.
We're going to have we will
come back to public comment but
now we have to get to our 230
special order.
MADAM Clerk, can you call our
230 special order?
>> yes.
Today's 3:00 230 special order
is recognition of commendations
.
>> right.
And I believe we're going to go
with d-10 supervisor walton
first.
>> thank you so much,
PRESIDENT, MADAM And colleagues
today I rise to honor the
patriot tears market and mary
and edmund woo if they could
come up to the podium please.
>> on MARCH 1st, 1960 jack
and phong will laid the
foundation for what will become
a beloved cornerstone of the
petro hill community with deep
roots in san francisco's
chinatown where jack gained
experience in the grocery trade
and phong worked diligently
in a garment factory.
They followed their dream of
building something of their own
when the opportunity arose to
purchase a small neighborhood
store and petro hue.
They took a leap of faith that
will shape the course of their
family's future together.
Jack and phong, who owned
and operated the potrero
terrace market with unwavering
dedication raising their
children in the aisles
and behind the counters.
>> after school, mary edman
and their siblings pitched
in learning not only the ins
and outs of the business but
also the values of hard work,
family and service.
>> over the decades the store
stood witness to history
including the 1970s era patty
hearst kidnaping ransom that
called for feeding the poor an
effort that took place just
across the street.
>> the wolf family also shared
a warm and lasting friendship
with the family of O.J. Simpson
further rooting their store
in the vibrant, diverse
tapestry of portrayal hue.
As jack phoned gracefully aged
mary and edmund stepped up to
carry the legacy forward,
eventually being entrusted with
the ownership and stewardship
of the store.
Through all the years the heart
of the business remained
unchanged.
It was always about the people
.
>> the friendships formed.
The stories share and the
support exchanged between
neighbors made the store much
more than just a place to buy
groceries.
It became a community
institution.
Today we commend the entire wu
family and marian edmund wu for
their lifelong commitment to
patrol who put preserving a
legacy built on love labor
and deep community ties and for
continuing to honor their
parents vision.
Their store has nourished
generations not only with food
but with connection, kindness
and care.
The bond shared between this
generation of store is an
example of how cultures can
come together in community.
I would argue that there is no
better example of asian
and black solidarity in a
neighborhood.
Even as a young child in patrol
hill.
We knew that jack and fong
loved being a part of the hill
.
We celebrate and thank you so
much for your extraordinary
service and for the rich
history you carry forward.
>> thank you.
>> superpole supervisor walton
.
I appreciate your support
and I'm honored to receive this
award.
My mom and dad have been
looking down.
I'm sure they'd be proud.
So on behalf of me, mary and my
brother robert, we appreciate
your support.
>> thank you.
You kidding me?
Huh?
This way.
So no terrorist right on this
map.
All right.
>> next up from district seven
supervisor melgar.
>> thank you so much, PRESIDENT
Mandell.
Man.
So today I have at the pleasure
of doing accommodation for
chris dudas that if you could
come up with your family and we
basically have the whole inner
sunset neighborhood here
in support.
>> and so chris dudas side is
an engineer, artist, public
space advocate and longtime san
francisco resident.
Chris has lived in the inner
sunset for 52 years.
>> during this time he has used
his many skills to bring beauty
and accessibility to our city's
public spaces.
Since 2012 chris has led the
public bench project.
this incredible organization
builds and provides public
benches free of charge to any
san franciscan who requests
one.
Expanding access to quality
public spaces regardless of
means.
>> chris began his bench making
career in 1977.
The first one he designed was
an easy to clean model for a
friend's veterinary clinic.
But he wouldn't stop there.
He ever the engineer chris
continued to build benches
refining his designs by
spending countless hours
in golden gate park studying
different models.
In 2003 the bracken parks
department began a project to
expand the golden gate skating
area.
And chris, a long time at
roller skater offered to create
the benches to populate the
renovated space.
Those benches are still enjoyed
by skaters today.
>> in 2012, after receiving a
design challenge from a friend
chris created a new portable
wooden bench design.
Realizing that these benches
could be built to distributed
with relative ease, chris
started the public bench
project.
He then launched a website
where community members could
request a bench or point find
plants to build their own.
Since founding the public bench
project, chris has built
and installed over 210 benches
.
These benches can be found
in nearly every neighborhood
in the city but in the inner
sunset we have many of them
and they're all beautiful.
>> although the public bench
project accepts donations to
cover the costs of the
materials, chris only at chris
has donated all of his benches
free of charge.
He not only makes the benches
themselves but also decorates
them.
>> chris's benches can be found
in a rainbow of colors
in beautifully painted designs.
>> he currently makes
and installs about two benches
a month.
>> chris is a fierce advocate
for increasing access to public
spaces by creating benches for
all who want them.
Chris hopes to provide san
francisco's diverse communities
with physical space for
connection and relaxation each
and every day.
San franciscans of every age,
background and demographic
enjoy chris's benches whether
used by roller skaters
and golden gate park elders who
need to rest after climbing a
particularly steep hill or
people who simply want to take
a break and watch the fog roll
in.
Chris's benches have provided
an invaluable public service.
Chris through your devoted
and incredible volunteer
efforts you have demonstrated
to add your creativity
commitment to community
building.
>> deep love for the city
and its residents.
It is my honor to recognize
your efforts and thank you for
all you have done to bring joy
and connection to everyday san
franciscans.
>> thank you.
>> I would like to thank you
very much supervisor melgar.
And I'd like to thank all of
the supervisors for their
giving me this honor.
And at the same time I would
like to thank all of the
supervisors because I am sure
you are all here because you
believe you can make our city
and the world a better place.
Personally I started working
in public spaces 40 years ago
and I've been on the board of
about a dozen different public
space organizations including
san francisco tomorrow.
>> and then as the supervisor
so aptly mentioned because of
my profession I made custom
machines for silicon valley.
They would ask me they bring me
a problem.
I give them design.
If they liked it I'd make it.
And I bring it out and install
it.
And my machines picked up
everything apple made.
Cisco made sun made,
hewlett-packard made in another
hundred and 50 countries
companies.
The benches were an offshoot of
this.
And I find that we all have
skills.
And if we can take those skills
and put them toward helping
others then we can make a
better place.
In any case, I want to thank
all of the people that have
accepted my benches.
The benches are only place
where people request them.
I make sure that there's a
reasonable place to put it.
if there is a problem we just
remove it.
And with that today I delivered
two more batches so I'm at 215.
And I don't know how much
longer I'll be doing this until
I can't stand up anymore.
Very briefly I'd like to
introduce my wife karen to
start.
She's chair of the citrus
stuart's who you honored
earlier this year.
She couldn't make it because
she was on the border helping
with people trying to get
asylum coming into the country.
So as you can imagine, there is
a cloud over our house now.
>> thank you very much.
But karen is standing right
behind you.
>> I just wanted to acknowledge
thank you.
>> thank you so much.
You took half my speech.
>> thanks so much.
Thank me.
Thank you for being here
and take a picture with all the
people.
Should I do this?
Do the trump thing.
>> let's go outside because you
have so many people here.
Okay.
All right.
>> and I think we will go back
now to public comments.
So folks want to line up.
Over on the side we can do this
until 3:00 when we have another
special order.
Please proceed.
>> hello, my name is jeremy.
If you see no, I've lived
in the bay area my whole life.
>> I grew up in san francisco.
I went to oldham in daly city
up until I was in second grade.
moved to the presidio in 1998
with my father norman if you
know who worked for the
presidio trust.
>> and my mother judy and you
know who is a 30 who had 30
years of service at the
department of veterans affairs
here in san francisco.
I'm really off and I'm trying
to contain myself because as I
feel there's been a lack of
leadership in terms of our
mayor our mayor hasn't spoken
out against trump and I'm
getting really worked up
because my parents put in time
and they actually cared and put
in service for this country
and this city and this area.
This is my dad and my dad
passed away about two years
ago.
He had stage four lung cancer
and before that he was the
chief shop steward at the
presidio trust.
Now that means he argued a lot
and he didn't see eye to eye
with people but he was forced
into situations where you have
to talk with people you don't
agree with.
>> and I have no idea what the
mayor is doing.
I see his instagram message
some multiple times asking
and calling for a town hall.
I haven't heard part my excuse
me permit language but I am
frustrated.
I don't like the fact that he's
a comes from that type of money
in terms of stepson of a
billionaire or I don't know
anyone who has that type of
money.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> speaker your time is
expired.
apologies for cutting you off.
>> everyone is receiving two
minutes today.
Next speaker yes, I'll make
this brief.
DECEMBER 4th why last year 24
2024 while visiting a bay area
I had a contact that was a
little bit troubling over the
local library in san francisco
.
Since that time I visited I've
submitted several records
requests under sunshine
and received very few records
in response.
Subsequently I put a complaint
found out about a complaint
that I could put into the task
force and have been struggling,
have been languishing with that
process.
Last week I attended a task
force meeting last wednesday
and overheard the chair talking
about the troubles they were
having sunshine with ethics
just sort of administrator at
the staff level dismissing
referrals to them and one of
the things that I took away
from that meeting was that
because sunshine has a city
attorney contact at that
meeting was that it would be a
very simple to me training to
bring or and business meeting
to bring those two together
and work out the differences
and and really streamline that
so I'm looking for advocates
who are really interested
in that process and assisting
me to also get my issue
through.
I've been languishing for four
months with this.
I haven't had a administrative
hearing nor have I been able to
get my issue in front of the
task force is being stopped at
the staff level as well.
>> so with a show of hands of
anyone on the board of
supervisors who's interested
in assisting me, I will
consider this is not a question
or answer time.
>> this is your time to provide
comments.
No I didn't ask for a question
I just asked your speakers
time's expired.
>> next speaker please.
>> good afternoon.
Board of supervisors.
For the record, my name is
chris ward klein.
I also go by sergeant klein of
the united states marine corps
active duty.
Prior to this meeting I sent
each of you an email with a
packet of a plan.
It's not my plan.
It was put together by the
department of justice and the
department of defense for san
francisco to get 1 billion plus
dollars.
That would pretty much solve
all your budget problems.
So I would speak with the
mayor, speak with the
comptroller, speak with the
city attorney's office.
That needs to happen.
It will happen.
I'm getting money from night
veterans are going to get money
from that.
Citizens in san francisco are
going to get money from that.
You can build your seawall with
it.
You can use it to fix your
budget.
So I don't understand why it's
so complex to submit a claim
for over $1 billion.
why is that?
Isn't that claim already
submitted?
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> your next speaker.
Good afternoon supervisors.
>> my name is clint and I'm a
member with pen voice of san
francisco.
I'm a registered nurse but I'm
forced to be a stay at home mom
because I don't have child
care.
>> even with the help of baby
pepsi funds, the choice is
supposedly funded.
Childcare is limited especially
for nontraditional hours.
>> we need to expand parental
choice by allowing city
vouchers to several kinds of
care.
>> please keep the promise to
our children of universal
access to quality childcare
and allow for parental choice
that meets the family needs.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is lourdes alarcon.
I'm a resident of san
francisco.
For many years.
>> I have two children.
I'm also an educator and early
care provider.
And I am really happy to
announce that baby see was a
great proposal for our children
to get served especially the
ones that are young like one,
two, five and baby see is one
of our best.
One of your best decisions
and investment.
But I also want to say that we
still need like to get like
fair salaries.
>> our salaries are so
providers are really low
and also we're advocating for
the waiting list their waiting
list is always there.
The children are still waiting
to get education to get care.
And I'm here to ask you please
support the early care
and education.
Reward the educators as they
deserve and also take care of
the educational system
and early care and education
again.
>> thank you very much for your
attention.
I hope we have your support.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
Happy week of the young child.
And we also want to acknowledge
supervisor melgar for
sponsoring the resolution for
the week of the young child.
>> we are proud to have passed
baby prop c in san francisco
and it started a trend in the
bay area.
Oakland also passed theirs.
Sonoma county and other
counties are looking at us
and how we implement this
special funding for child care
.
>> we want to make sure that we
honor the charge given to us.
>> we want you to keep the
promise to our children of
universal access to quality
childcare and allow for
parental choice that meets
families needs.
So we have baby prop c but the
choices of parents are still
limited.
>> our city vouchers can only
go to specific kinds of child
care.
And like queen earlier said as
an hour in her schedule could
be mostly nontraditional and we
want to make sure that we also
address that need.
>> but most of all, we
appreciate your support for for
making sure that baby c is
preserved and for passing the
budget last year that saved the
the principle for baby prop c
and only is dangerous.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker supervisors.
I'm alan wang.
I'm the policy director for
children's council san
francisco and also here on
behalf of the S.F. Advocacy
coalition.
And so we're very happy to have
this resolution sponsored by
supervisor melgar on the agenda
today to support week of the
young child.
We've made a lot of progress
in our investments with our
baby prop c supporting
investments in early care
and also pre-kindergarten.
We want to ensure that we get
our supervisors to see what's
going on in your child care
sites, in your districts.
We've we're going to be sending
invites if we haven't already
to sign you all up to visit
some of the childcare
facilities that are in your
districts and we're looking
forward to hosting you all
and having you join our
coalition.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> hello, my name is liam
mckeever.
i live in district six.
I'm a transgender latin x
homeowner.
>> I am very disappointed
in san francisco which
proclaimed itself a transgender
sanctuary city and a
transgender sanctuary state.
>> and yeah, I just read about
how san francisco has taken
more money away from trans
people trans groups including
money away from a bunch of
other suffering oppressed
communities as well.
>> 950 thousand dollars from
the transgender variance
and intersex justice project
which focuses on black
and trans people black
and brown trans people.
$250,000 from the transgender
district.
>> you should be spending more
money.
money on trans people, on black
people, on brown people.
On undocumented people.
On chinese people.
On on lgbtq people in general.
On people who have hiv because
the federal government is
attacking all of us right now.
Okay.
There are many people on this
board who fall into that
demographic.
>> you should be very vocal
and very loud and put your
money where your mouth is if
you open your mouth for us.
Some of you stood on a stage
with scott wiener saying you
protect trans youth.
What have you done since then?
>> did you even do anything
visible on trans day of
visibility?
>> I doubt it.
i think one of you posted
something on a social media
accounts.
That's so pathetic.
So pathetic.
You canceled the gift program
last year which was for very
poor, very, very vulnerable
trans black, brown trans people
.
Do you know do you know what
happened to them?
Did you ever follow up?
Do you know the consequences of
your actions?
>> you are hurting people.
People need to be mad at you
not trump or musk.
Next speaker please.
Very emotional there are so.
>> good afternoon supervisor my
name is ace the fillmore
quarter investor I'm trying to
make this as fast as I can to
all of you lawmakers,
legislators we in the fillmore
need your help.
>> we need your support.
>> I'm I got a big case load.
I don't know if I'm going to be
able to talk about the fillmore
sinner.
We got the safeway issue.
We got public housing issue.
We got the we got a department
here our city dealing with our
issues about the oh jesus scuse
me the juneteenth.
>> so I'm sick and tired of
being sick.
It it's no reflection on our
new administrators.
This has been going on for
years before y'all got here.
>> but the mayor you must care
because he's a millionaire.
>> you could get your other
buddies to help us and I'm I'm
not being facetious.
I'm being truthful.
we need help in the fillmore
now the mayor came a couple of
weeks ago and I videotaped it
also videotape when ed lee came
in.
>> I'm going to compare it
and we still got problems.
>> we got big issues I haven't
named them all but we have
issues that need to be
addressed immediate.
Lee we got collective impact.
Lee hill once we got the issue
we got so many I only got 30s
but I had to be crystal clear
to this city and county the
city by the bay I am the
fillmore corridor ambassador I
MAY not be the mayor or the
supervisor or the power but I'm
here to tell y'all we need help
from this administration.
My name is ace and I'm on the
case live in direct and you
don't have to adjust.
>> you'll sit.
Thank you for coming.
Next speaker good afternoon,
supervisors my name is anthony
huang and I'm an advocate with
chinese for affirmative action
.
I'm here to voice strong
support for a resolution
condemning PRESIDENT Trump's
unlawful and cruel use of the
alien enemies act to detain
and deport non citizens.
I thank supervisor melgar for
her leadership on this critical
issue the trump
administration's action
deporting over 200 venezuelan
nationals without due process
are uncosted to tional
xenophobic and echoes some of
the darkest moments in U.S.
History.
We've seen this before during
world war two the government
used the same law to detain
japanese german and italian
immigrants leading to mass
incarceration and injustice.
San francisco has stood as a
city of inclusion and immigrant
rights.
We must continue that legacy by
rejecting these harmful
policies and fuel fear
and racial profiling.
I urge the board of supervisors
to approve this resolution
and reaffirm our commitment to
protecting our immigrant
communities.
Thank you for your leadership
on this critical issue.
>> thank you for your comments
and just to clarify, folks are
waiting we're going to have to
interrupt public comment at
3:00.
So that's probably our last
public comment in this bit.
You know, we have okay, we are
talking here to talk we have a
3 P.M. Special order sir, we
talk please continue with your
public comment and then we're
going to go to 3:03 P.M.
Special order.
Good afternoon supervisors.
My name is nick g.
I'm an advocate with chinese
for affirmative action a civil
rights based organization
in san francisco's chinatown
and co-founding partner of the
stop aapi hate coalition.
>> today we stand in strong
support of this resolution
condemning PRESIDENT Trump's
use of the alien enemies act to
kidnap and deport non-citizens.
We are incredibly grateful to
supervisor mel ga's leadership
in introducing this critical
and timely resolution in a
moment when immigrant rights
continue to be under attack.
>> we must fight back.
The unlawful detention
and deportation of over 200
venezuelan nationals without
notice hearings or legal
representation is a blatant
violation of due process and an
attack on immigrant families.
>> this is not just about one
group.
This is about all of us.
When the government targets one
community it sets a dangerous
precedent that puts all
immigrants and people of color
at risk.
History has shown us the harm
that xenophobic policies like
these can cause from the
incarceration of
japanese-americans to today's
mass deportations.
The city of san francisco must
take a stand and reject the
shameful history from repeating
itself.
We must continue to actively
support and defend our
immigrant communities
regardless of immigration
status and oppose the
escalation of federal immigrant
enforcement.
It is for these reasons I urge
the board of supervisors to
approve this resolution and we
look forward to continuing to
work with your offices to
protect san francisco's
immigrant communities.
Thank you.
Thank you for your call.
All right, sara, we're going to
have to take a break in public
comment because we have a3p m
special order.
>> you can come forward three
you will not serve.
>> I thought I was sorry but
you don't harvard people.
We really wanted to something.
>> do you give them all the
that come with I'll come over
so it could have a family.
>> all right.
Thank you.
We are now going to go to our 3
P.M. Special order, MADAM
Clerk.
Can you call that?
>> yes.
Items 19 through 22 are
associated with the appeal of
the conditional use
authorization for the proposed
project at 4100 third street to
convert an existing two story
over basement mixed use
building.
Item 19 is a hearing of persons
interested I don't know
approves a see you
authorization item 21 requires
a higher vote threshold of not
less than two thirds or equal
to the members to disapprove
the conditional use
authorization and item 22
directs the clerk to prepare
findings if the board wishes to
disapprove this conditional use
authorization.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
So colleagues, we have before
us a hearing on the appeal of
the conditional use
authorization approval for the
proposed project at 4100 third
street.
>> there is a standard way that
we would proceed on hearing an
appeal like this that would
involve proceeding as follows
we would give the appellant up
to ten minutes for a
presentation and we would then
open public comment for
speakers who want to speak
in support of the appeal.
Then we would provide up to ten
minutes for a presentation from
the planning department
and then we would provide up to
ten minutes for the project
sponsor.
Then we would take public
comment from speakers who want
to speak in support of the
and support the project sponsor
and opposition to the appeal.
And finally we would provide up
to three minutes for rebuttal
by the appellant.
I, I believe that the that the
apple kins believes that this
matter that MAY be withdrawn by
the appellant if it is not I
believe that the applicant MAY
be wanting to request that it
be continued.
>> but I guess we can proceed
and hear from the appellant
and then this board can decide
what to do if we actually need
to here have a full hearing on
this matter.
So that's how I'm proposing
that we proceed unless there
are objections.
>> I know that was about as
clear as mud.
I apologize colleagues.
I will explain it again if I
need to explain it again.
Seeing no objections, the
public hearing will proceed as
indicated and is now open
and then I don't know if
supervisor walton if you want
to.
>> nope.
All right then.
And no one else is on the
roster so I will ask the
appellant to come forward
and present their case and you
MAY have up to ten minutes.
>> I'm sorry, PRESIDENT Mendoza
and I thought I was going to be
able to answer your question
before you guys took that
order.
But since we move forward I
just wanted to say good
afternoon PRESIDENT Mandolin
supervisors and members of the
public thank you for giving me
the opportunity to speak today
regarding the appeal for the
conditional use permit for 4100
third street at the space that
is not only a historical gem
in the baby community but as of
2024 was one of the last
remaining saloon restaurants
in san francisco still
operating in its original form
with sro units that serve
working class residents above
the commercial space.
This building has stood for 144
years providing community meals
,drinks and affordable housing
for people who built
and sustained the city last
year I was part of a group of
local makers who shared the
space and had invested time
and resources in dividing the
space with hundreds
and thousands of dollars of
city grants before this
building was sold thus once
again displacing vulnerable
entrepreneurs who ingenuity
shines at local farmers markets
and fears the transition from
the space was sudden and a
cloud of uncertainty was placed
over a new owners of the space
and JANUARY a friend of mine
reached out to me to inform me
that the building had already
went before the planning
commission with zero little
community outreach.
As someone who is deeply
concerned about our affordable
housing crisis, those baffled
at why anyone would approve the
loss of our units in a city
with a housing shortage crisis
in a neighborhood which has
doubled its homelessness since
covid the type of protections
which are available in other
neighborhoods are not codified
in bayview not or nor are there
systems in place which provide
checks and balances to properly
inform the planning commission
and things happening in our
community.
So as you can see this
conditional use permit is about
more than just one building.
It speaks to the larger system
that brought me here before you
today a system that too often
feels outdated, inaccessible
and adversarial turning
neighbors such as myself an ftc
into the opponents instead of
collaborators.
But I view this moment as an
opportunity, a spark and a
beacon of what's possible when
we come together to fix a
broken systems with equity care
and shared vision.
I want to take a moment to
express my deep gratitude to
supervisors danny sauder,
martin and mo gar shyanne chan
,bill bellomo and jackie
fielder for your leadership,
engagement and thoughtfulness
throughout this process.
I look forward to working with
all of you guys on broader
board to continue addressing
the complex challenges of our
communities face and help make
san francisco more inclusive,
equitable and vibrant city for
everyone.
And it's my hope that following
today we can work with the
board to bring our
administrative code four fee
waivers into compliance with
state law so that no other
indigent person must face the
kind of obstacles I had to
overcome simply to be heard by
you today I also urge the
planning department to conduct
more rigorous and proactive
research and historically
significant properties
especially those were where the
date of construction is unclear
.
Thanks to the dedicated
and knowledgeable staff at our
san francisco public library I
was able to verify through
seller's records water permits
and insurance logs that this
building holds deep historical
value or reflects a period of
our city's founding an
architectural structure that is
the city that is quickly
disappearing.
And furthermore, I'd like to
encourage the planning
department's equity task force
to ensure it truly reflects the
full diversity of san francisco
and allows a larger community
process not just people that
are hand-selected by various
officials to be on some of
these decision making groups as
we move forward with d-10
zoning and other issues like
that.
>> I'm I want to also say that
I would like sorry I even so I
would also like to say I'm
grateful for the leadership of
the friends of children of san
francisco for working with me
over the past several months to
ensure that practice of the
week sorry to ensure that we
can preserve space for some of
just those displaced
entrepreneurs post renovation.
I'm encouraged that historic
elements like the building's
exterior and butler elevator
will be preserved and we are
actively exploring ways to
offer culinary classes for
families and build workforce
pathways for youth interested
in the culinary art.
This partnership between
myself, big black brunch
and friends of the children
shows what's possible when
community and development work
hand in hand with mutual
respect and collaboration to
lead the way.
I'd like to in the spirit of
our agreement that we made I
would like to withdraw my
petition for the appeal being
that the issues that I raised.
Ftc has agreed that they will
honor the historic preservation
and have pleasantly and warmly
invited some of our merchants
back in to use the space once
they're done with their
renovations.
So thank you again supervisors
the public and friends of the
children.
All right.
Thank you, MISS Brackett.
>> all right.
So MADAM Clerk and MR. City
attorney, you're going to need
to help me out here a little
bit.
We have an appeal before us.
We have a public we are in a
public hearing the appeal the
applicant appears to desire to
withdraw the appeal is that
just done?
>> good afternoon, supervisors.
Deputy city attorney brad
rusty, I think you should
confirm with the project
sponsor that they're on board
with the withdrawal of the
appeal and then proceed to
public comment on this item
before you take action.
>> okay.
And would we would we take
action on the item table?
>> I think the action would be
to affirm the planning
commission's decision and table
the other items.
Okay.
All right.
Thank you MR. Razzi.
Hello.
You are with the applicant?
>> yes.
I'm susan collette, executive
director friends of the
children S.F. Bay area and I
affirm all right, so the the
applicant and the appellants
are in agreement and we can
open this item to public
comments if there's any member
of the public who wants to
speak to us on items 19, 20, 21
or 22, please line up.
And since no one is doing that
public comment or this public
hearing is closed and then I
think I would be looking for a
motion to a to approve the see
you authorization which means
approving item number 20
and tabling items 21 and 22.
>> so move moved by supervisor
walton is there a second
seconded by supervisor fielder
and MADAM Clerk can you call
the roll on that motion on that
motion supervisor walton walton
I supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood supervisor
mendelson hi mendelson I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor cheryl cheryl either
tonight all right then without
objection item number 20 is
approved items 21 and 22 are
tabled and I think we can go
back to public comments.
>> those who have not provided
public comment please line up
now.
We will continue with the
public commenters 21 1820.
>> go ahead.
Thank you.
My name is professor stephen
zunes.
I teach at the university of
san francisco and I am want to
weigh in.
In addition to some comments
made last week for special
memorial recognition of the
late david hardt so who died
about a week and a half ago.
Those of you who heard the
testimony earlier know of as
his commitment to peace
and justice, his early arrest
in the civil rights movement
and opposition to the vietnam
war.
But he continued and he was
arrested just a few months ago.
You know, protesting arms
shipments to foreign
governments that were engaging
in war crimes.
But his advocacy for nonviolent
resistance in support of
freedom and justice was
refreshingly non-ideological.
As an american, he felt a
special obligation to oppose
war and defend human rights
and washington war
responsibility.
But he also defended the rights
of those struggling against
anti-american regimes as well.
Long before most people even
heard of kosovo, he was perhaps
the single most active
supporter in the united states
of the nonviolent struggle by
the ethnic albanian majority
struggle against the oppressive
apartheid like system imposed
by the serbs.
>> and more people listened to
him.
We could have avoided the rise
of the armed wing of the
independence movement and the
11 week nato bombing campaign
that followed.
>> his commitment was not just
to causes but his generosity to
people here in san francisco
was was immeasurable.
>> he and his wife jan allowed
the rooms in their house in the
heat to be made available for
writers, scholars, activists,
workers and volunteers in the
nonprofit sector of otherwise
have had trouble affording to
live here.
And thanks to his generosity
enabled countless people to
contribute to the political
and cultural life of the city
as well as humanitarian work
who otherwise would not have
been able to do so.
So thank you for your attention
to this and for honoring a
great san franciscan who's
going to be sorely missed.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> my name is jenna from the
san francisco public defender's
office and I rise to support
the resolution condemning the
invocation of the alien enemies
act.
Trump's use of the alien alien
enemies act is a shameful
resurrection of a racist
episode in our nation's
history.
We last invoked this act based
on a fraudulent pretext to
incarcerate japanese community
members during world war two.
It was morally wrong then it is
morally wrong now.
>> as a public defender you
might expect for me to talk
about due process especially
in light of the supreme court's
decision last night lifting the
restraining order
and permitting the continued
kidnaping and disappearance is
under the aca to continue so
long as individuals are given
so-called due process.
But do not be fooled.
>> due process is a hollow
promise from this supreme
court.
I have defended immigrants
in deportation courts for over
ten years.
I have seen the due process
that has allowed my clients to
be detained for years
in private jails only to be
ordered removed by judges who
denied 99.9% of asylum claims.
>> due process is not enough
here.
It has never been enough when
we are talking about demonizing
people in order to justify
cruelty against them.
As we speak we are rendering
people to a mega prison whose
conditions are designed to
inflict pain.
>> we're talking about cells
without mattresses, without
sunlight and where people are
being forced to eat food off
the floor like dogs.
We're talking about a place
where the salvadoran PRESIDENT
Has boasted quote we are going
to wipe out these murderers
and their collaborators.
We will put them in prison
and they will never get out.
>> so what we need is not
procedure.
It is safety.
The alien enemies act makes us
all unsafe.
>> it is not only venezuelans
but any have to fear comments.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisor.
My name is francisco carty.
I'm the manager of immigration
defense unit at the san
francisco public defender's
office.
I'd like to thank supervisor
melgar for putting forward this
resolution for our supervisor
who've co-sponsored the
resolution against the alien
enemies act.
I just want to say one thing
briefly.
We are living through an
assault on our fundamental
freedoms and an attempt at mass
deportation in a way we've
never seen in this country.
We can stop this only if we
raise our voices only if we are
brave enough to raise our
voices.
And this resolution is just one
step of many.
We need to take because it will
if we do not raise our voices.
These things are going to
continue to happen and we've
proven our ability over
and over and over again to
defend fundamental due process
and freedoms not only for
immigrants but for all people.
And this is an issue where all
of us should be united on
because the trump
administration could come after
immigrants.
But there's nothing to stop it
to come against anyone that it
perceives as an enemy which is
exactly what this law was
designed to address.
So I just thank you so much.
I invite you to join us and I
also ask with all of my heart
for the mayor's office to take
a stand.
>> we haven't heard from you
much on this issue.
We need to hear from you.
>> please.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
Good afternoon.
My name is ashley milburn and I
am a early child care provider.
I'm standing here with the
black early educator policy
council, a group that
continuously advocate advocates
for black early educators
and the curious and courageous
children of san francisco.
Convened by children's council
of san francisco.
I'm proud to say that I'm a
native who resides in bayview
hunters point district team.
For this week of the young
child I wanted to call
attention to the need to
wholeheartedly support black
children and their families.
With everything happening
in our economy.
Our black children needs the
adults to come together and be
the leaders they entrust us all
to be and ensure our children
are secure, more safe
and poured into with educators
who are trained and equipped to
deliver the trauma informed
and culturally competent care.
We thank the board of
supervisors us for their hard
work helping save baby property
funding during the last year
budget season.
Yet there's a lot of other
there are a lot of early black
educators still struggling
greatly with equitable
compensation.
Opportunities for higher
education earned credentials,
early playing fields for credit
good credit and homeownership.
And honestly the same needs
that we've been having for
leading for generations.
We thank the department of
early childhood, childhood
and city and city and county of
san francisco for their current
support.
But we employ you to support
more in public investments
and as you continue to recruit
and retain black early
educators such as myself
and not only the black children
of san francisco but our
children of san francisco.
Let us take care of those who
take care of our future.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
Board of supervisors.
My name is tammy cake and I'm
here to talk to you about
special spo a special police
officers association and is it
academy for security guards are
individuals that have to better
themselves by training
and practicing the ideology
that from each person you can
gain by examining the beliefs
then and learning from our past
choices that it is better to be
positive and not to let the
choices dictate our past is a
failure that society tends to
push you to believe in.
If you learn one thing let it
be that life is a place to know
you are the creator of your own
destiny.
Learn from the practice
in training that you are able
to be better if you want
and believe in that ideology it
makes the actions you learn to
know how to change and the
situation because it's better
when you know how to do better
then you can teach others that
matters.
The choices that you make can
have a negative effect a
positive effect by strive, by
striving to through this
practice and training you can
learn how to grow in a positive
manner.
I think one of the best
and most important choices are
made by members who are getting
through through self
betterment.
>> you can learn how to choose
the best way to handle a given
situation and that choice MAY
be to ask for help.
And what I was trying to get to
was that esperar needs your
help and a lot there are losing
the building on 14th and folsom
and I was hoping thank you for
your comments.
>> apologies for cutting you
off.
>> we are providing everyone
two minutes next speaker
PRESIDENT Mendelsohn
and members of the board of
supervisors.
My name is joyce nakamura and I
have been a resident district
three for over 30 years.
>> first of all I'd like to
thank supervisor melgar and all
of the sponsors of the
resolution condemning PRESIDENT
Trump's use of the alien
enemies act.
>> I'm thankful that this
resolution calls on our
congressional representatives
to repeal the aca.
>> baby wipes supporting the
neighbors not enemies act.
>> this power must be taken
away.
It must be stripped from the
PRESIDENT As witnessed by
trump's recent use of the aca
to arrest without due process,
detain and deport venezuelan
immigrants.
Invocation of the aca without a
declaration of war by congress
and denial of fifth amendment
rights of immigrants is
unconstitutional.
By 1942 my grandfather had
spent nearly 30 years 30 years
investing in the life
and economy of this country,
building his farming business,
building community with his
peers and raising his youngest
as four U.S. Born children.
>> this life was destroyed
overnight.
He was denied citizenship.
He was branded as an enemy of
the U.S. By the aca.
>> while U.S. Born mother was
also targeted as disloyal, my
grandfather lost his business
and had to start all over again
in his early 60 is to rebuild
his life's work.
>> the alien enemies act must
be repealed so the PRESIDENT
Cannot abuse the law
and further violate our
constitution.
>> it is overly broad and can
be used to target individuals
based only on national origin,
only on national origin like my
family was.
>> thank you.
>> thank you very much.
Next speaker.
>> thank you supervisors.
My name is carl takei.
I'm the program director for
civil liberties and community
safety at the asian law caucus
and I'm also the great
grandchild of jiro seagull, an
immigrant who was arrested
under the alien enemies act
during world war two.
I'm here to thank supervisor
melgar for your leadership
and to speak in support of the
resolution condemning PRESIDENT
Trump's illegal invocation of
the alien enemies act.
>> my great grandfather
immigrated from japan in 1904
to live the american dream.
Over nearly four decades he
built a thriving sweater
knitting business in seattle,
greatly grieved his wife's
death from tuberculosis
and raised their five american
born children to adulthood.
But in JANUARY 1942, his dreams
were shattered when two fbi
agents came to jerome's house
and arrested him as an enemy
alien in front of his children
as he sat in a prison camp.
His business was shut down
and his pride was crushed.
Jiro did not live to see the
end of the war.
He died of a broken heart
in spring of 1945.
By illegally invoking the 1798
wartime power PRESIDENT Trump
is seeking to silence dissent
and disappear.
parents, siblings, neighbors
and coworkers without due
process.
Based on who we are or where we
came from we cannot let this
happen again.
On behalf of aoc, I urge you to
keep the memory of my great
grandfather in your hearts
and thank you for passing this
resolution condemning this
illegal abuse of power.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> thank you.
Good afternoon supervisors.
My name is carolyn goosen
and on behalf of the public
defender's office and public
defender value I wanted to give
my utmost thanks to supervisor
melgar and her staff jen lowe
and emma hare for their
leadership in bringing forward
the resolution condemning
PRESIDENT Trump's use of the
alien enemies act.
I also want to thank carl
and joyce for sharing those
very powerful stories and thank
you as well to the nine
supervisors who has cosponsored
it.
>> just as thousands of san
franciscans took to the streets
this weekend to oppose the
cruel and malicious actions of
this federal administration, we
are all collectively taking a
stand today through this
resolution to oppose the use of
this terrible act to deport
without due process.
Over 200 venezuelan immigrants.
The use of this act is
dangerous and should shock the
conscience of every american.
>> as has been mentioned, some
of those who were essentially
kidnaped by the U.S. Government
and sent to el salvador have
pending civil court dates to
obtain immigration status.
>> these individuals are now
now being held indefinitely
in a country that suspended its
own constitution with no speedy
trial rights, no independent
judiciary and in a massive
prison that has been condemned
by human rights organizations
for torture tactics and other
human rights abuses.
The trump administration's use
of this act is horrific,
terrifying and outrageous.
But it has been inspiring these
last few weeks to see so many
come out in opposition in our
city.
Immigrant rights leaders
and particularly japanese
american community members
and elders who have been vocal
and passionate in their
opposition to this act as they
are all too familiar with the
disgusting abuse of power that
has connected to it.
So thank you supervisors for
your support and we urge a
unanimous vote.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> my name is janelle brown
here on behalf of the black
early educator policy council,
a group that advocates on
behalf of black early educators
and children in san francisco
convened by children's council
of san francisco this week of
the young child.
>> I especially want to pay
homage to the black early
educators as they have been the
backbone of the childcare
industry since its inception.
They need pay equity and more
economic supports to sustain
themselves in this field.
Home ownership and financial
literacy workshops could
greatly help black early
educators expand their family
childcare businesses which
would open up more childcare
spaces for black families.
We thank supervisor shimon
walton who participated in a
site visit and mom anita's
loving arms childcare last year
in district ten and we thank
the rest of the board of
supervisors for their hard work
helping to save baby prop c
funding during last year's
budget season.
But a lot of our black folks
still struggle greatly with
facility upgrades.
>> with all the rollbacks
in the national education
landscape, our black children
are very vulnerable.
We thank the department of
early childhood and the city of
san francisco for their current
support.
But we need as much public
investment as possible to
continue recruiting
and retaining black early
educators to not only support
black children but our children
in san francisco.
Again, we thank supervisors
melgar filter sadr and chan for
sponsoring this week of the
young child resolution.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
Good afternoon supervisors
rebecca jackson, vp of reentry
at community ford and co-chair
of the san francisco women's
housing coalition.
>> I can't help be caught up
in the plight of the immigrants
of our trans community and I
just want to remind everyone
that women are silently being
put to the test as well.
>> on the federal level.
And so I am here begging you
guys to unanimously support the
resolution.
Now is our time that we can
declare san francisco as a
sanctuary for women who are
seeking safe housing.
And two weeks ago we were
gathered outside.
>> thank you to all of you who
supported us and that over 20
organizations saying that women
and the time are now and we
have a plan and this resolution
introduced by supervisor chan
is just a call for us to
coordinate and work together
and a promise that you all see
us.
We are 40% of the unhoused
population and we need to work
together.
We can make a big impact but we
can't be afraid to say the word
woman and all that that means
here and now.
And that's an inclusive
statement.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is liz winograd.
I work for the low income
investment fund and also a for
c pac where we focus on
expanding access to high
quality early care
and education in san francisco.
I want to thank you for your
steadfast support of your use
of our youngest children
and their families and for
recognizing this nationally
celebrated week of the young
child which with this important
early childhood education
resolution thank you for your
leadership and the critical
funding from baby prop c we've
been able to make great
progress.
These dollars have helped
educate and support early
educators increase salaries to
aid in recruitment
and retention and most visibly
expand access by building
and renovating childcare
facilities across the city.
This year alone we will have
invested almost $15 million
into new sites and quality
improvements that directly
benefit our children's learning
environments.
As we move deeper into budget
season we know there's still so
much more to do.
We hope you'll continue to
protect this funding and stand
with san francisco's children,
families and educators.
Thank you again for your
continued support in early care
and education.
>> he supervisors.
Good afternoon.
My name is alex mic house came
at the san francisco early care
and education advocacy
coalition.
Thank you so much for
celebrating and recognizing
early care educators, young
children and their families
today with the resolution
celebrating the week of the
young child.
>> we also thank you for your
work hand in hand with us
in the past years to protect
child care funding.
Those funds have done some
pretty amazing things
and they've raised many in our
workforce out of poverty level
wages.
They've helped incentivize
future entrants into the
workforce to secure the future
and increased access so that
san francisco's children can be
set a set up to be successful
and thrive just to name a few.
As we head into another
uncertain budget season I have
to reiterate as listed how
important protecting baby
perhaps the funding is.
That funding will allow some of
the programs aforementioned to
continue and new programs such
as providing supports to
children with special needs for
example to emerge the dreams of
many children, families
and educators depend on that
funding.
>> so thank you again for all
you do.
I look forward to working with
you all and the department of
early childhood to continue to
make san francisco a national
leader and early care
and education and I'm behalf of
the coalition we look forward
to hosting you all later this
month for U.S. Site visits
in your district.
>> thank you all.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker hello.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is sierra fisher and I
both live and work in the
mission district district nine.
So I want to thank you guys for
just considering our week of
the young child resolution or
item fit 35 and being here
today to celebrate early career
educators, young children
and their families during the
nationally recognized week of
the young child.
>> I'd like to reflect on the
hard work, collaborative spirit
and commitment to early care
and education demonstrated by
helping to secure child care
funding in the last year's
budget cycle ultimately
curtailing cuts which would
have been detrimental impacts
to the expansion of this
community.
>> as you'll undoubtedly hear
today, baby c funding has meant
the world to this community
increasing educator wages to
livable and more dignified
compensation.
Expanding to new sites
and increasing access to
affordable and quality
childcare across the city.
>> these funds ensure proper
investments are made into
improving young children's
lives and setting them up for
success in their most critical
and formative years.
So thank you again for
continuing to uplift the
children and families
and educators within our san
francisco community.
We look forward to having each
of you at our upcoming visits
across a child care site
in your district.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Mandolin and board of
supervisors.
My name is sarah hicks kilday.
I'm with the early care
educators of san francisco
and the san francisco advocacy
coalition and I want to speak
first on commending you on
putting forward resolution 31
and recognize the good talk
from many people in the public.
>> I am here to speak to
resolution 35 appreciating you
for recognizing the importance
of early care and education
during the wake of young
children.
I want to both thank you
and remind you of last year's
agreements to make sure the
property funding is maintained
for its purpose for early care
and education and we'll work
with you towards that
commitment in this hard budget
budget year.
Again the over a hundred
educators that I've met with
during the last week have both
expressed their appreciation
for the compensation roll out
that has come so far.
The professional development
pathways have come so far as
well has talked in detail about
how that could be made even
more robust and talked about
how their services could be
made more quality with the
increased compensation ability
to move on to specialize
in certain areas and integrate
that into the teams they work
with to serve special needs
children.
Their ideas are innovative
and have never been in a place
where they feel ready to make
them really move into action.
I look forward to visiting site
visits and hearing more about
this during the few months
ahead.
>> thank you again.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker hello
supervisors my name is ryan
hazleton.
I'm a resident of d-essex.
I'm the executive director of
mariposa kids and d9 and a
member of c pac and I'm here to
speak today in celebration of
week of the early child and the
proclamation for early
childhood education in our
city.
I think the board for the
previous support of investment
in early childhood education
and as the school district
really focuses on their success
I want to remind everyone here
that investment in early
childhood education leads to
kindergarten readiness which
can improve school district
performance overall and to
bring in the energy that we saw
over the weekend here in civic
center.
>> let's go into budget season
with the idea of hands off baby
prop c thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hello, my name is
virginia taylor.
I'm senior policy advisor at
safe and sound safe and sound
is san francisco's child abuse
and neglect prevention
organization.
I'm here today for the family
services alliance which
represents over 40 family
support organizations serving
more than 30,000 san francisco
families each year in support
of the week of I'm here
in support of the week of the
young child resolution.
The family services alliance
wants to express our heartfelt
gratitude to our city's early
childhood educators and family
support workers for their
dedication to making a positive
difference in the lives of san
francisco's youngest children
and families.
We extend our gratitude to the
board of supervisors for this
resolution as APRIL is also
child abuse awareness month
quality child care and family
support are crucial in enabling
families to stabilize their
lives which prevents child
abuse and neglect.
The city's investment in these
services have contributed to
the city's 60% reduction
in child abuse and neglect over
the past 20 years.
Thank you to the board and the
department of early childhood
for your leadership.
But as we celebrate these
successes we recognize that our
work is far from over.
Building on the progress made,
the city must continue to
support children from birth to
five and their families stable
families and thriving children
create a safer san francisco.
We look forward to continuing
this essential work together
ensuring that every san
francisco child from 0 to 5
and their families can thrive.
>> thank you for your support.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hello.
Good afternoon.
>> my name is vanessa boehm
and I work for the central
american resource center.
>> we are an immigrant rights
and advocacy organization that
has been serving low income
families and immigrant families
in san francisco and the
greater bay area since 1985.
Through a variety of direct
service programs we are here
today to express our support
for the resolution condemning
trump's aca as an organization
offers low cost legal
immigration services and as
part of a greater network of
other local organizations
providing critical legal
immigration support services.
We work day in and day out to
protect the rights of our
immigrant community members the
invoking of the alien enemies
act against people who migrate
and those who protest the
current federal administration
denies them of their rights to
due process and much more.
>> we wholeheartedly believe
that the city of san francisco
should protect immigrant
rights.
We know that our communities
support you all and will
continue to support you all as
you take further action to
protect immigrant rights.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon board of
supervisors.
My name is linda mac burch
and I am an early childhood
educator.
I am also a resident of san
francisco, a proud resident.
>> I have been here for over 30
years.
I am also a member of the black
early education policy council
which is convened by san
francisco children council.
>> and as I said earlier, I am
a resident here also.
But this week of the young
child I especially want to call
your attention to the support
of black children and families
and not just black children
and families but all of our
children.
>> and I also want to thank you
for prop c all of your hard
work and just for your support
that you have continued to give
us.
But we know that we're we're
in some difficult times in some
lean years but we still need to
plead to you and carla to you
to please continue to support
us.
We thank you for your
department of early childhood
education, the city of san
francisco for their support.
>> and as I said earlier, we
need to keep supporting our
black children there, our
future, our early educators.
We need we still need equitable
pay.
We need financial literacy.
>> we need as we know we live
in the bay area and housing
court costs are very, very high
especially for a family child
care center providers.
So again, I want to thank you
and continue to support us as
we continue to support you
and the great city of san
francisco.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker hi, my name is
nathan potash and I'm the rabbi
out of coal valley here in san
francisco.
I'm here to support the board
of supervisors resolution
declaring wednesday, APRIL 9th,
2025 education and sharing day
san francisco.
And I want to thank board
PRESIDENT Super supervisor
management for his leadership
the river rabbi menachem mendel
schneerson of righteous memory
taught that every individual
and in fact every individual
action has an impact on the
entire universe.
The rabbi emphasized the
importance of education
and good character.
And the rabbi taught that
education in general should not
be limited to the acquisition
of knowledge and preparation
for a career.
Instead, the educational system
must pay more attention to the
building of character with
emphasis on moral and ethical
values.
>> over the last four decades
the us congress has set aside
education in sharing day
marking the anniversary of the
rabbis birth.
In tribute to his commitment to
teaching the next generation of
america of american's noble
values and morals this day
provides americans the
opportunity to pause
and recognize our
responsibility to ensure that
our young people have the
foundation necessary to lead
lives rich in purpose
and fulfillment.
Last week mayor lurie signed a
proclamation designating
wednesday, APRIL 9th, 2025 as
education and sharing day
in san francisco.
And I'm standing before you to
share my support for the board
of supervisors resolution
initiated by board PRESIDENT
Supervisor management.
This resolution is a call to
all residents of san francisco
to reflect on the vital role of
education in preparing our
youth to be the leaders of
tomorrow with an emphasis on
inspiring them of their moral
and ethical obligation to serve
a cause greater than themselves
and instilling in their minds
and hearts the empowering
message that one act of
kindness can tip the balance of
the world in favor of
positivity.
MAY our city serve as a beacon
of light for people of all
faiths and walks of life.
>> thank you for your comments
.
Next speaker.
Hello everyone.
My name is babette brackett.
I wanted to thank supervisor
mel garg and for her resolution
in support of rejecting trump's
cruel use of wartime actions to
deport non-citizens.
I'd also like to thank
supervisor shimon ward walton
for his support of the
african-american early
childhood alliance and I also
urge that you support those
and new and upcoming childhood
educators with a pathway for
them to own their own homes
and buildings and spaces so
that we can have more childcare
facilities and home based
childcare for families.
I know that typical 9 to 5
childcare doesn't always work
for all families.
They have different working
hours and these home based
childcare centers kind of fill
that gap and that need.
But I'm actually here today to
urge you to be urging all of
our supervisors today to for
each of you to review the
OCTOBER 1st, 2024 ocr
commission meeting specifically
items five c and five d as they
highlight glaring failures
in our city systems
and oversight processes.
These items underscore what
many of us already know our
most vulnerable residents are
being left behind while
developers and property
management companies with city
contracts continue to operate
without proper accountability
or compliance.
Yesterday you heard directly
from residents of the alice
griffith affordable housing
development about the
uninhabitable conditions they
are forced to endure
and silence conditions that
continue and include broken
elevators, ada violations
and even feces on the
children's playground.
This is not just unacceptable,
it's unconscionable and these
families live in a development
that is less than five years
old and yet the conditions
resemble those of neglected
bent buildings many decades
older.
Following the OCTOBER 1st
meeting, rlc the commission
voted to approve the creation
of a housing task force an
important step forward.
That task force was intended to
not only address the issues
and crisis at alice griffith
but also to work to drafting
new legislation that would
allow oci to maintain
conservatorship over their
sites.
It builds ensuring quicker
and more effective responses to
future issues.
>> however, despite the promise
thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
My name is barbara walden.
i work for immense inspiring
success and I'm also here on
behalf of the black early
educator policy council, a
group that advocates on behalf
of black early educators
and children in san francisco.
Convened by children's council
of san francisco.
Thank you for celebrating early
care educators, young children
and their families today during
this national recognized week
of the young child.
And your hard work helping to
save child care funding during
last year's budget season
margin analyzed communities are
being targeted and children
especially black children are
the most at risk and vulnerable
of these marginalized
communities.
Headstart and other subsidized
child care that provides for
these communities are also
under attack.
Now more than ever we need to
stand together.
The city must show us how much
they truly value child care
despite current challenges.
I am very appreciative of the
department of early childhood
and all they have done for
educators and children via baby
prop c implements asian
compensation support workforce
pathway stipends for educators
sequel and other amazing
initiatives.
San francisco is a model for
child care in the nation.
We thank dc and san francisco
for their current support.
But we need as much public
investment as possible to
continue to recruit, retrain,
retain and support black early
educators.
to not only support black
children but all children
in san francisco.
The san francisco A.C.E.
Advocacy coalition will be
inviting all of you to visit
child care sites in your
districts.
I look forward to having you
visit some of my campuses
in the near future.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> hi everyone.
My name is robin kropp and I'm
here to say a few words about
my friend david hart.
So and I thank supervisor
randleman for reading and in
memoriam for him today.
>> david and his family live
in the haight-ashbury for 50
years.
He was a local and a global
peace activist and I think the
first thing I want to say is
I'd like to invite people to go
listen to him in his own words
on youtube.
You can look for him reading
the first couple chapters of
his book waging peace global
adventures of a lifetime
activist.
>> that's him talking to us.
There's also a wonderful
interview of him JANUARY 20th,
2020 with him talking to the
peace workers organizations,
his stories are marvelous.
Are so inspiring.
And then also yousef here
in our city gave him a lifetime
achievement award for his work.
>> and I recommend that you
watch that because we have at
least 15 leaders talking about
him in his work and how they
were affected by him.
>> so he has so much to teach
about nonviolence and I think I
just feel like I want to see
him keep teaching.
He used to say just a few
people could could encourage
more people could encourage
more people.
And one of my favorite stories
was when he was integrating the
lunch counters in arlington,
virginia when he was a student
at 20.
>> and a man came up to him
with a switchblade knife
and threatened him.
And david looked at him
and said friend, do what you
believe is best to do.
But I will still try to love
you.
>> and the man's hand shook any
dropped the knife and walked
out and that showed david the
power of nonviolent and loving
response.
>> and so he basically I think
he had a lot of successes like
here at the comfort naval
weapons station.
Just a few of them blockaded.
>> and then when brian wilson
had his legs cut off, 10,000 of
us went we tore up the railroad
tracks and then 50 peace
organizations were there for
two and a half years and they
stopped those weapons from
going to central america.
That's one story out of
hundreds that I could tell.
>> so thank you very much.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker well, I'm torn
between two.
I want to talk about how I pray
for tom homan and and PRESIDENT
Trump that I thank GOD for
and religion and there's really
nothing more important that
palm sunday is coming up.
So I'm going to talk about
religion now in our holy
religion it's called
christianity.
We believe that jesus actually
wrote a donkey two of them
in fulfillment of a prophecy
in zachariah.
And as he was writing the
donkeys they said hosanna to
the son of david.
Blessed is he that comes in the
name of the lord and jesus made
a very telling statement as all
of them are.
He said if these were all
together to hold their peace
the stones would immediately
cry out.
>> now in psalm 118 I'm not
sure when that was written
and by whom it was written but
it says the stone which the
builders refused is become the
head stone of the corner.
This is the lord's doing and it
is marvelous in our eyes.
This is the day which the lord
has made.
We will rejoice and be glad
in it.
Save now I beseech the oh lord
.
Now when they said hosanna
that's what they were saying.
They were saying save us save
us from, you know, the roman
empire and their their cruelty
and government is designed by
GOD to protect the people from
the criminal elements.
Now we probably have 4040
million illegal aliens that
have surged the border
and become felons because they
have searched the border
and you know, in fulfillment of
joe's prophecy, you know, when
they stole the election in 2020
to surge the border.
>> but this is also prophetic
because the sun is being
darkened right now.
When I think about letitia
james, she's such a hypocrite
quoting scriptures.
>> GOD jesus said zero
tolerance for hypocrisy.
See by the grace of GOD I'm not
a hypocrite.
>> I'm telling you the truth.
Okay?
Jesus saves.
>> next speaker, please.
>> my name is richard.
Steve peterson.
>> I've obviously talked here
before and I want to express my
disappointment that the city is
not granting permits, permits,
permits, permits, permits.
>> how are you going to build
in this city if you don't grant
permits?
I've been waiting eight years
for a permit although I paid
the planning department over 15
thousand dollars.
I had to finally change my
profession.
Now I'm attempting to be a
fortune teller and I paid my
money for my fortune telling
permit.
It still is not issued permits
permits, permits.
Oh and a shout out for jimmy
haas.
>> love you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Next speaker.
>> hi.
Good afternoon.
>> board of supervisors.
Where to begin?
So the other day I was
in downtown san francisco at
union square, one of my
favorite restaurants the cafe
central.
I was at the counter ordering
breakfast or brunch, whatever.
>> and before I knew it out of
the blue I was assaulted.
I was physically assaulted from
behind.
And before I could realize what
was going on I look over my
shoulder, there's a arm
reaching over me.
Somebody is reaching for the
cash in the register tail.
And once I realized it was a
robbery, I stopped that guy.
And I held him down until the
police got there.
Unfortunately, that's not the
first time that's happened.
>> that's the second restaurant
robbery.
I've stopped in union square.
Several months before that the
pine chris diner was robbed.
And I chased that guy down from
geary street to powell street.
>> the newspaper made me out to
be the bad guy.
A few months later they let
that same robber out of jail.
He went back to the same place
and assaulted an innocent
latino woman.
GOD would have it that I was
just so happened to be walking
by.
And I placed him under
citizen's arrest a second time.
The chaos and lawlessness
happening in our community is
widespread.
It's not just one neighborhood
in a common theme throughout
all of this is drugs.
And we need to stop the drug
dealers.
>> we need to deport the
fentanyl dealers.
Not give fentanyl dealers the
same rights and respects as
indigenous native americans.
We need to deport the fentanyl
dealers.
And we need to remove enough
from our community once and for
all.
Fear not showing up on
playgrounds and in schools.
>> children are overdosing.
You guys are supposed to be our
leaders and every day we're
walking the streets and we're
seeing the decline of western
civilization and everywhere you
look are the signs of.
Thank you for your comments.
There are all right.
I believe that and unless their
other speakers ransacked their
public comment is closed
and ransacked.
I'm live on top of the hill.
>> all right.
The last time we passed the
most common points to any of
these places look around
everywhere you are.
>> all right.
So we give everybody we give
everybody two minutes
and you're welcome to come back
.
But we got to go on to our
meeting.
>> that we're not.
All right.
Let's go to our for adoption of
that committee reference agenda
items 26 through 38 items 26 to
30 eight were introduced for
adoption but without committee
reference.
A unanimous vote is therefore
required for adoption of a
resolution.
First appearance today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
sorry to jump the gun there
looks like supervisor melgar
has something.
>> yes.
I'd like to separate items 3031
and 35 please.
>> all right.
We got 30, 3135 and nobody else
has anything.
>> all right, so on the
remaining balance of the items,
MADAM.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll?
>> yes.
Supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder.
I supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor gentleman I men's
woman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor cheryl
cheryl either tonight's all
right without objection
resolutions are adopted and the
motions are approved and then
MADAM Clerk can you please call
item 30?
>> yes.
Item 30 is a resolution waiving
the department of public works
permit fee and board of appeals
fee associated with a detroit
detroit steps project
supervisor melgar thank you so
much in working with our city
attorney this week we
discovered a procedural error.
So I need to send this
resolution to committee to
budget and finance so I'd like
to make a motion that we send
this to committee.
>> all right.
There's motion to send this
item to committee.
is there a second was the only
motion just send it.
>> thank you.
No motion and and it's going
okay.
Great.
Thank you.
Any member can do that or I
need to do that without any
member.
>> that's right.
>> because it's okay.
Thank you.
All right.
There we go.
Thank you.
Former PRESIDENT Walton.
All right, MADAM Clerk, can you
please call item 31?
>> yes.
Item 31 is a resolution
condemning PRESIDENT Trump's
use of the alien enemies act to
deport non-citizens as an abuse
of power and threat to our
constitutional order as melgar
okay.
>> thank you colleagues for
your support and co-sponsorship
of this important resolution.
We are living in dangerous
times.
The alien enemies act is being
misused to justify mass
deportations under the false
pretense that the violent
actions of a few constitute an
invasion by the country of
venezuela.
>> this act has a painful
history, particularly for
japanese americans that should
not be overlooked.
It was used as the basis for
one of the most egregious acts
of our country's history the
mass arrest of japanese
immigrants and the incarcerate
and incarceration of
japanese-americans.
>> this action represents yet
another example of dangerous
overreach of the executive
power direct and a direct
attack of our constitutional
protections.
We must stand against it
and call on our current
congressional leaders to repeal
all the alien enemies act
through the passage of the
neighbors not enemies act,
which is H.R. Bill 630
and senate bill 193.
>> I want to take a moment to
appreciate everyone who came
for public comment today
and who has helped in drafting
this resolution and to come out
in support.
Some of these are the
immigration unit of the san
francisco public defender's
office.
Public defender manuel raja
and others in his office carl
takei with the asian law caucus
and molly morosi at the a
japantown task force not joyce
nakamura the neo miramonte
community coalition in all of
its members organize asians.
>> and I also want to thank all
of the japanese community aapi
leaders and the immigrant
rights leaders who held a press
conference in japantown two
and a half weeks ago to call
attention to this issue
including john osaki satsuki
ina dean ito, grace shimizu,
reverend deb lee bay area day
of remembrance and the neo
manchu community coalition
and organizations.
>> lastly, I would make a
motion to adopt an amendment to
clarify a word in their
resolution to accurately
reflect that during 1944 the
alien enemies act was
authorized to arrest japanese
immigrant community leaders
immigrant community leaders.
This change is on page one line
25 and I have shared that
language with everyone.
Thank you PRESIDENT Mendelsohn
.
>> thank you supervisor melgar,
thank you for this.
For this resolution.
I think we're going to be
finding new offenses weekly
pretty much to be to be calling
out and condemning and I know
there's a I am having the
desire not to hyperventilate
and overreact to things but
this is extraordinary.
I mean I think 70 something
like 75% of these folks have no
criminal record.
You know some of them are being
carted off because they have
tattoos.
>> a particular person is not
you know, a gay hairdresser who
like you go back there his
social media over like ten
years and it's very gay and not
very gang and you know, if you
think that you know this can't
you know if this is happening
to people who are illegally
seeking asylum or status here
in this country, this can
happen to any immigrant.
It can happen actually to any
native born person because
they're not using due process
to determine who gets sent off
to this hellhole and of a
prison in in el salvador
without any rights at all.
And how long are they going to
be there?
So thank you supervisor melgar
.
I think that we need a second
for your I'm for your proposed
amendment seconded by walton.
I think we can take that
without objection and then we
can.
So the motion the without
objection the the resolution as
amended and then I think we can
take the amended resolution
same house, same call without
objection the amended
resolution is adopted.
>> all right.
Applauses okay.
We're not about actually we're
not supposed to break.
It's actually okay.
And then MADAM Clerk, if you
could call item number 35.
>> item 35 is the resolution
celebrate early care educators
and families of young children
during the week of the young
child APRIL 5th through APRIL
11th, 2025 and reaffirming the
city's commitment to
establishing a universal
inclusive early care
and education system that
expands access, reduces
barriers, addresses
affordability and leverages
strategic partnerships.
>> supervisor melgar okay
colleagues happy week of the
young child in the city
and county of san francisco.
I'm excited to celebrate this
annual week to honor all the
hard work of our early
educators and the families of
young children.
>> thank you to all the
advocates who are here today.
Many of us will be visiting
early care education sites
in our respective districts at
this month and it's honestly
one of my favorite things to do
because I love seeing the
toddlers and the babies.
>> it is magical to look at our
quality early education
in nurturing environments
provided by people who are
passionate and care about our
children, early care educators
are essential to our city but
are so severely underpaid
and underappreciated for the
work that they do.
This workforce is predominantly
women of color which further,
you know, highlights the
disparities in inequities
in our society.
Still, san francisco remains a
leader and I would be remiss
not to acknowledge the
champions for childcare who
have come before us and paved
the way for where we are today.
Former PRESIDENT Normani
and supervisor jane kim in the
voters of san francisco who
passed a historic baby prop c
with a goal of raising wages
for these workers with a
formation of the department of
early education early care
educators are seeing increase
in their wages and more
investment in their
professional development and we
have seen a decrease of 73%
in the waitlist since 2018.
However, we still have a lot of
opportunities for growth
and expansion so that we can
fulfill the promise that we
made to the voters for
universal child care.
>> this includes expanding
slots for families like middle
income families but also for
babies and making room for the
tiny ones.
We need to remove more
barriers, leverage partnerships
with employers
and organizations and I also
believe that creation of these
slots is a way for our downtown
recovery.
This is where we need them.
We also should be looking at
more interventions for children
with special needs children who
are different and more focused
invest ment in our black
indigenous english language
learners and pacific islander
families.
I want to express my deepest
gratitude to our early
educators for their work and of
course acknowledge the advocacy
of the child care planning,
care and advisory council.
Thanks for being here.
Parent voices the black early
educator policy council the low
income investment fund.
Children's council and other
organizations that have been
relentless in their fight for
universal early care
and education.
>> and I hope as we go through
this difficult budget season we
don't turn our backs on our
promise.
>> thank you colleagues for
your support.
>> thank you supervisor melgar
for this resolution and and
with that and if anyone else
has anything to say, I think we
can take this item.
>> same house, same call
without objection and the
resolution is adopted and also
the okay.
>> and MADAM Clerk, do we have
any imperative agenda items?
>> we do not have any apparent
imperative items today.
>> okay then MADAM Clerk, can
you please read the
in memoriam?
>> yes.
Today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individual.
On behalf of PRESIDENT Mandolin
for the late DR. MR. David hart
so and I believe that brings us
to the end of our agenda, MADAM
Clerk.
>> is there any further
business before us today?
>> that concludes our business
for today.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
As there is no further business
we are adjourned